So while you guys were gone, I went on Wikipedia
and looked up Osiris, because when I did the
research for this book it certainly wasn’t
possible to get access to that kind of information
instantaneously. And the stories that are
laid out in there… there’s a thread that
runs the stories that are laid out there,
that’s quite similar to the one I told you,
but there’s all sorts of details that are
very radically different. And so, I don’t
really know what to say about that. And you
know, part of the reason that people like
Joseph Campbell and Carl Jung and… there
was an original anthropologist, an armchair
anthropologist, who wrote a book called The
Golden Bough, whose name escapes me momentarily
[it’s Sir James George Frazer], but it was
one of the first attempts to do a cross-cultural
categorisation of mythology, and to look for
underlying commonalities. Now the problem
is, you know I told you about Naomi Klein
going down to Argentina and looking at the
factory through her particular lens. The problem
is that when you develop a lens and then you
look at things through it, you may just see
what that lens heightens, you know, and I
think that’s a criticism that could be leveled
against the sorts of things that I’m telling
you about. You know, that I’ve cherry-picked
certain stories and interpreted them in certain
ways so that they fall coherently into a scheme
of thought. And so I’ll tell you some of
the things that I do methodologically to protect
myself against that, insofar as that’s possible.
So there is this idea in psychology called
the multimethod-multitrait method of construct
validation, which is, you know, a God-awful
agglomeration of jargon. But it actually means
something. And it was the construction of
two psychologists back in the late 1950s,
Cronbach and Meehl, who were interested in
what psychologists meant when they said something
existed. Like say, anger. Is that a real thing?
Well what do you mean, ‘thing’? What is
it that you’re talking about? What is anger,
exactly? I don’t mean as ‘anger’, but
as an idea. What sort of idea is the idea
of anger or the idea of anxiety or the idea
of sadness? Or the idea of self-esteem or
self-competence or any of these things that
psychologists talk about as if they’re realities.
Well, some realities are very tangible, right,
and it’s somewhat easy to come to agreement
about the contours of their existence, and
the borders, but other things are way more
difficult than that. And so their idea was
that if something actually existed, you should
be able to measure it multiple ways, using
multiple techniques, and still get the same
answer. And so, your senses do that. You have
five of them. And the reason you have five,
apparently, is because evolution has determined
that if you only had four you’d die more
often. So it seems as if you have five separate
sources of information that all lead to the
same conclusion. You can be relatively certain
that the conclusion’s that reached is real.
Well, the multimethod-multitrait method is
an application of that idea to construct validation,
which is like… you could think of anger
as an idea, as a construct, it’s a terminological
issue. You just define it as a construct,
a psychological construct. How do you know
if they’re real? Well the idea is it’s
very complicated. You have to measure them
in multiple ways. All the ways you measure
them have to give the same reading. Then you
have to show that that idea is the same in
certain ways as other ideas that it’s related
to and different from other ideas that it’s
not related. So let me give an example. There’s
a construct: ‘neuroticism’. And you might
say, well there’s another construct: ‘depression’.
Well then you might say, “well are those
separate or are they the same?” Well that’s
a tough one, because in many, many ways they’re
the same. Are they different in any important
ways? Well, the way you do that technically
is you would measure neuroticism however you
were going to measure it. Maybe I’d have
you tell me how neurotic you were using a
questionnaire, and then I’d have your friend
tell me and maybe your parent, so we’ve
got a pretty good triangulation on your neuroticism.
Then I have them do the same thing, all those
people do the same thing with regards to your
levels of depression and anxiety. Then I’d
use both those measures to predict something
else, like how well your life goes in terms
of career over the next ten years. And if
neuroticism predicted and depression predicted,
so they were correlated, then I’d think
well there’s some relationship. Then I’d
look at them at the same time. If I predict
with neuroticism and then I add depression
to the mix, does that give me more predictive
power. It’s sort of like does A = C or does
A + B = C? That’s all you’re asking in
a regression equation, roughly speaking. Well
if A = C is just as good as A + B = C, especially
if the two things are also correlated (depression/anxiety
and neuroticism are going to be very highly
correlated, like 0.7, something like that),
you might say well those are the same things.
Just because they have different names, it’s
not helped. And part of it is, it’s a pragmatic
conceptualisation of reality, it’s like,
is this categorisation structure good for
something?
Okay, so anyways, I’ll unpack all that and
say, well part of my rules for determining
whether these things were useful or not was
to see if the ideas apply across multiple
levels of analysis. So that’s why I told
you about the conceptual, so that’s sort
of the cognitive psychology, and then the
neuropsychological, so there’s some input
of brain research. And then the narrative
or mythological, and then the cross-cultural
and think well those all stack up in a certain
way so that if you look between all of them
you can see a pattern. And it seems to me
increasingly unlikely that that pattern would
be there across all of those levels at the
same time. Now you could say well, you know
that depends on how good you are at weaving
a story. But at some point, encapsulating
that many phenomena and weaving a coherent
story out of them if such a thing doesn’t
exist, it seems to me to become cognitively
impossible. You just can’t do it unless
there’s actually something there. And of
course everything I tell you also is a simplification.
It has to be. Because you could spend your
whole life investigating any of the things
we’re talking about and so what I’m hoping
is I’ve extracted out the central issues
of these multiple levels of analysis and put
together, each of them support all the others.
Anyways, who knows? You know, I don’t know,
but so far so good. Okay so this is a cool
representation, I really like this one. This
is called The Open Virgin. And it’s a 14th
or 13th century sculpture, if I remember correctly.
It’s made out of wood. And these things
were actually… this isn’t the only one
of them. They were a form of religious interpretation
that had different exemplars. You could find
different ones of them online. This is brilliant,
this bloody thing, as far as I’m concerned.
So let me show you this figure again. So basically
what you have here, in this figure, this is
a world conception. And the world conception
is roughly: there’s an individual, positive
and negative, he or she is in a cultural sphere
that’s positive or negative, that’s embedded
in the world outside of culture, that’s
positive and negative, and all of it comes
from potential. That’s the idea.
Now, this map shows all of the positives and
negatives in relationship to one another,
and you see it’s not perfectly symmetrical
and the reason for that is, as far as I can
tell, the adversarial element of the individual
is the thing that generates the tyrannical
element of culture. And that’s the thing
that gets in your way of establishing a creative
relationship with what you don’t know. Well,
anyways. Here is a manifestation of that,
I believe. And I like this manifestation because…
like, it’s obviously Christian, but not
exactly. It’s more mythological than Christian.
And the reason for that, well, is quite obvious.
So the superordinate figure is Mary, the feminine.
Now you think, well it’s amazing the person
who carved this didn’t get burnt up at the
Inquisition, because it’s a radical idea,
but it’s just an indication of how the mythology
can change the causal relationship between
these different elements.
So you have Mary there, she’s the ultimate
in femininity, the ultimate feminine deity,
but only the positive side. And then within
her, so it’s like Nature opens itself up,
benevolent Nature opens itself up, and what
you see inside is culture, that’s God the
Father, holding the individual, and the individual
in this case is the crucified Christ, which
is a wonderful conceptualisation as far as
I’m concerned, because of course that is
what life does to people, that’s why that’s
such a powerful symbol. It’s like, you know,
Christ is the person who has to face the reality
of his own death, voluntarily or involuntarily,
who’s betrayed by his culture, betrayed
by his friends, it’s sort of like he’s
exposed to the most torturous elements of
individual being. And simultaneously, at least
in principle, transcends them. Well it’s
like you bloody well better do that because
otherwise, well what’s going to happen?
You’re done if you don’t do that. And
it’s even worse, it’s not only that you
fail, that’s just the beginning of it. If
you can’t transcend the tragedy of your
being then you get corrupted. I see this happening
to people happening all the time.
So you know, if you’re suffering and you
can’t cope with it, generally speaking what
happens is that it embitters you. And once
you get bitter you get resentful, and once
you get resentful you look for revenge. And
that can just get completely out of hand.
Now that’s a quick trip to the worst suburb
of the Underworld, that’s for sure. So you
know, it’s not only that if you don’t
manage this transcendent act that you’re
swamped by the tragedy of your life. You’re
swamped by the tragedy of your life, and then
that corrupts you, and then you start working
to make everything even more tragic than it
has to be. And so I think that’s why in
medieval Christian conceptualisations in particular,
the idea of hell, the idea that you were destined
to hell was worse than the idea of dying.
And it’s a strange idea, you know, because
you think (this is what the terror management
theorists think too) is that “there’s
nothing worse than the fear of death!” It’s
like, that’s wrong. They don’t have the
right imagination. There are lots of things
that are worse than the fear of death. I’m
not trying to trivialise the fear of death,
obviously, but I don’t think it’s very
difficult to understand that there are some
things that you would rather die than do.
I mean I’m sure that I could get you guys
to sit for fifteen minutes and say okay, list
ten things that you would rather die than
do. That’s easy. Especially if you’re
a parent. You can think of those things in
like no time flat.
Okay so that’s pretty interesting. So you’ve
got the superordinate feminine figure here,
which is not what you would expect from a
Christian representation, right? You’d expect
God to be on the outside, and then Mary and
then Christ, in all likelihood, although that
would also be a valid representation. Because
you can think of the mother as something that’s
protected by the culture. And supporting the
individual, because that’s basically what
this representation shows. But then you see
on the open sides, I really like this, I think
it’s so cool, is that you’ve got all these
people who aren’t archetypal figures, they’re
in a little crowd. And they’re gazing at
the central figure. And of course that’s
exactly what’s happened in Christianity
for two thousand years, right, insofar as
it has spread, is that for two thousand years
people have been looking at that image, which
is the crucifixion, transfixed by it. Well
why? Well, you know, for reasons that we don’t
understand. When everybody woke up in the
late 1800s and said, “why were we looking
at that for the last two thousand years?”
the first answer was “well we really don’t
have the foggiest idea”. It was just one
of the things that we did, roughly speaking.
It encapsulated people within the belief system.
So that’s another good example, anyway,
of how this archetypal imagery can manifest
itself, say spontaneously, in the imagination
of an artist. And the thing is, that’s a
sacred image. And it is an actuality, that’s
what it is. What it shows is, well there’s
a superordinate, transcendent, natural order
that has a beneficial element that we associate
with femininity, and inside that there’s
a supportive culture that’s properly nested
if things are organised properly. And it’s
both of those things that provide support
for the suffering individuals. It’s like
yeah, that’s pretty much got it. Now that
doesn’t exhaust the meaning of this particular
representation, there’s a lot more to it
than that, but just that is not so bad.
And then, you know I can show you a more negative
representation, I think I’ve shown you this
before. Like this would be a representation
of the negative element of the feminine. And
so you have Kali here, and Kali is the goddess
to whom you make sacrifices and hopefully
if you make the right sacrifices, then Kali
turns into her positive counterpart. And you
know, you think, well that’s a… what…
how does sacrifice affect your relationship
with the gods? Well first of all there’s
no gods and second of all, well then what
the hell are you doing with the sacrifices?
But it’s pretty straightforward. We’ve
already talked about this at length. You do
make sacrifices, all the time. And what that
means is that you act as if you can have a
relationship with being. You assume that if
you withhold certain things from yourself
now, that you will improve your relationship,
both with nature and with culture. And I already
told you guys that as far as I was concerned
that was the most stunning cognitive discovery
of mankind. It’s the discovery of the future.
And it’s the discovery of the relationship
between the present and the future. You know
it’s such an amazing idea, that you can
alter your behaviour now, and it’ll pay
off in a year. God, that’s not obvious.
It’s certainly not… animals don’t think
that way. You know, some of them act that
way, like bees and so on, but that’s just
built right into their behaviour, as far as
we can tell.
So anyway, so there’s Kali. And you know,
she’s a spider. She’s in a web of fire.
The fire is outside a web that’s made out
of skulls. She’s got weapons in her hand,
her hair is on fire. She’s got a headdress
of skulls. I mean, if you ever saw something
like that it would traumatise you so badly
you wouldn’t be able to get out of your
house for like five years. That’s exactly
what it is. That’s what it is. It’s a
representation of all of that that would traumatise
you if you encountered it. And you know, it’s
an attempt to encapsulate that as an image,
and what you could say, in some sense, is
that the people who developed this image were
attempting to conceptualise the class of all
terrifying things. And once you get the class
of all terrifying things conceptualised, you
could come up with the class of all useful
responses. And that would be something like
the proper way to behave, and sacrifice is
an integral element of that. It’s like yeah,
absolutely. Absolutely dead on. Unless you
don’t believe that sacrifice works, in which
case, what the hell are you doing here? I
mean, you know, you act out your belief. And
it’s a firm belief. And you would also say
that if things fell apart so badly that sacrifice
no longer paid off, your life would basically
become intolerable. Because it would mean
that you would have abandoned all sense of
control over the outcomes of your actions.
Well you can’t live like that, you’d just
die of stress. Well and as I said, she was
pregnant, she’s given birth to this unfortunate
character, who she’s devouring intestines
first. Like it’s a rough image. It’s an
image of the destructive element of nature.
And so that’s the negative side of the feminine,
we might say.
There’s a positive representation. This
is a Greek representation. That’s Diana,
or Artemis. I’m hoping I’m remembering
this properly. She’s multi-breasted. This
circle around her head is undoubtedly a representation
of her cosmic nature. So it’s like a halo
but the halo is basically a planetary body
like the Sun… a cosmic body like the Sun
or the Moon behind the head of the divine
individual with all of that power shining
forward. So it’s an attempt to use… you
know, if you look up at the Moon or you look
up at the Sun, there’s an element that’s
characterised by awe. You can’t help but
feel that, at least its beauty and power,
and sometimes it’s overwhelming. Well, you
take the representation of the personality
and you throw the representation of these
cosmic powers behind it, and it’s an attempt
to represent transcendent value. It’s very
intelligent. It’s brilliant, in fact. And
so partly what you’re trying to do as you
conduct your life is you’re trying to get
all of these archetypal forces in proper balance.
And I suppose in some sense to get them tilted
towards the good, if that’s possible. I
mean, that’s what this representation in
some sense, you might say… [looks for picture]…
yeah, you might say well if you got everything
ordered properly, this is what being would
be like. Still pretty rough, given that the
crucifix is at its centre.
Now I don’t know, you know, if you think
about it from a purely technical perspective,
roughly speaking, each of these archetypes
is split into positive and negative. You might
say, well, that’s just how it is. There
is no way that you can interact with all of
them so that the whole system tilts towards
the positive, you know. But I don’t think
that’s true. I think you can get them lined
up so that things tilt towards the positive.
And I think you can detect when that happens,
because those are the periods in your life
where you feel that you’re richly enough
engaged in what you’re doing and life is
meaningful enough, so that the rest of it,
the substructure that makes it necessary,
is worth it. It’s worthwhile, you know,
that the negative exists is okay given the
way that things are structured.
Now I think that whether or not that’s true
is in some sense the eternal question of mankind.
Can you organise your life so that it’s
good? Well, it seems like you can certainly
allow your life to degenerate so that it’s
terrible. That seems indisputable, right,
and there does seem to be an element of choice
in that, although, you know something terrible
can happen to you that you have no choice
of or control over. But it certainly seems
that you could do any number of stupid and
blind things that make everything worse. I
think that’s common experience. And I also
think you’d be hard-pressed to find anyone
who wouldn’t say that there were things
they did consciously and willingly, that were
of their own choice, that they didn’t have
to do, that made things worse. So we seem
to have some sense of our moral agency. And
we seem automatically to accept some responsibility
for the outcomes of our actions. And so partly
what that means is that we do believe that
we can make things better or worse. And I
suppose in some way that means that we believe
we can tap the whole archetypal structure
of being into the positive. Well I would say
if you drill down to the bottom of existentialism,
in some sense, that’s the question that
the existentialists pose, you know. Is there
a manner of conducting your life such that
it becomes… it’s not merely acceptable,
it’s more than that. You’d say yes, this
is how it should be.
What we’re going to do now, although we’re
not going to do it today, is we’re going
to start talking about other representations
of this sub-structure from other religious
traditions. And we’re going to also talk
about ways that you might relate to these
figures. Because one question might be, well
you’re part of your culture, and it’s
got an orderly element, and a protective element,
and a tyrannical element. Okay so what should
you do about that? You know, should you…
the tyrannical element is real and it’s
corrupt and blind, and so to the degree that
you identify with that, when you’re tyrannical
and corrupt and blind, but by the same token
you’re the fortunate beneficiary of tens
of thousands of years of cultural and technological
evolution and effort. And it seems to me that,
you know, you should be at least appropriately
grateful for that. And so then you’re in
a real position, because you have to be grateful
and happy for the thing that tyrannises and
controls you. Well, okay, that’s not an
easy thing to figure out, because those things
seem to conflict. So what exactly should your
relationship to culture be? Well, I think
there are myths that describe that quite directly.
And they take into account the corruption.
It’s not a whitewash. It’s like yes of
course this thing is dead and blind and corrupt.
Obviously. And you know, it’s foolishness
and wilfulness… it’s ignorance and wilful
blindness that make it that way, as well as
things merely getting old and falling apart.
So the fact that there’s some malevolence
at the bottom of it is also true. Should you
flee from that? Well, that isn’t what the
myths say. They say what you’re supposed
to do is, just like Pinocchio, you’re supposed
to go to the bottom of the ocean, to the most
monstrous possible part, and rescue your father.
That’s what you have to do before you become
an individual.
And I can’t see how that can’t be right.
In fact, I think that’s what you’re doing
in university, if you’re actually getting
a university education. What you’re here
to do is sift through the dead remnants of
the past and pull up what’s vital, that’s
so sophisticated and complex that there’s
no way that you’d be able to think it up
for yourself. But you know, it requires you
as the discriminating agent. You know, if
you read someone like Nietzsche or you read
someone like Freud, there’s lots to throw
away. It isn’t what you throw away though,
it’s what you keep that matters. And to
be a discriminating reader means that you
get rid of the dead matter and you keep the
gold. And you build yourself up a storehouse
of gold, and then you can live in the world.
And people often ask, what’s the purpose
of getting a degree in the humanities? Well
the answer to that is that if you’re properly
trained in the humanities, you know how to
live. Now that’s the same as having a job,
and you need to have a job. But you know,
knowing how to live is a more important thing
than having a job, even though having a job
is an important thing. And the reason for
that is that if you don’t know how to live
then things fall apart. And that’s not good.
And they can really fall apart, you know,
and part of the reason I think that this became
so much of an obsession for me is that I believe
that we don’t have a lottery of… we are
narrowing… we’ve become so powerful that
the consequence of our blindness is reaching
uncontrollable proportions. If you’re weak
and stupid, well you know, there’s only
so much damage you can do. But we’re not
weak, not at all. We have unbelievable power
at our disposal now, and a lot of weird things
are going to come down the pipes in the next
ten years.
The more people that have their act together,
the better. Because then things will be tilted
towards everything lining up in a positive
direction rather than being tilted in the
other direction. And that’s important. And
I think people can make a very powerful individual
contribution to that, wherever you happen
to be. You know, all of these myths always
say the same thing. They say that the future
of the world depends on individual choice.
And I think that’s literally true. So then
you might think, well you better put yourself
in a position where you make wise choices,
because if you don’t… we’ve already
seen what happens. We got a taste in the 20th
century. So, if you want some more of that,
you could certainly have it.